For the problem of dimensionality
对于降维问题来说
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
reduction, by far the
目前
most popular, by far the
最流行
most commonly used algorithm is
最常用的算法是
something called principal components analysis or PCA.
主成分分析方法(Principal Componet Analysis, PCA）
It In this video, I would
在这段视频中
like to start talking about the
我想首先开始讨论
problem formulation for PCA,
PCA问题的公式描述
in other words let us try
也就是说
to formulate precisely exactly what
我们用公式准确地精确地描述
we would like PCA to do.
我们想让 PCA 来做什么
Let's say we have a dataset like
假设 我们有这样的一个数据集
this, so this is a dataset
这个数据集含有
of example X in R2,
二维实数R^2空间内的样本X
and let's say I want
假设我想
to reduce the dimension of the
对数据进行降维
data from two dimensional to one dimensional.
从二维降到一维
In other words I would like to find
也就是说，我想找到
a line onto which to project the data.
一条直线，将数据投影到这条直线上
So what seems like a good line onto which to project the data?
那怎么找到一条好的直线来投影这些数据呢？
A line like this might be a pretty good choice.
这样的一条直线也许是个不错的选择
And the reason you think
你认为
this might be a good choice is
这是一个不错的选择的原因是
that if you look at
如果你观察
where the projected versions of the points goes.
投影到直线上的点的位置
I'm gonna take this point and project it down here and get that.
我将这个点 投影到直线上 得到这个点
This point gets projected here, to
这点被投影到这里
here, to here, to here
这里 这里 以及这里
what we find is that the
我们发现
distance between each point
每个点到它们对应的
and the projected version is pretty small.
投影到直线上的点之间的距离非常小
That is, these blue
也就是说 这些蓝色的
line segments are pretty short.
线段非常的短
So what PCA
所以 正式的说
does, formally, is it tries
PCA所作的就是
to find a lower-dimensional surface
寻找一个低维的面
really a line in
在这个例子中
this case, onto which to
其实是一条直线
project the data, so that
数据投射在上面  使得
the sum of squares of these
这些蓝色小线段的平方和
little blue line segments is minimized.
达到最小化
The length of those blue line
这些蓝色线段的长度
segments, that's sometimes also called
时常被叫做
the projection error, and so what PCA
投影误差
does is it tries to find
所以PCA所做的就是寻找
the surface onto which to
一个投影平面
project the data so as to
对数据进行投影
minimize that. As an a
使得这个能够最小化
side, before applying PCA
另外，在应用PCA之前
it's standard practice to
常规的做法是
first perform mean normalization and
先进行均值归一化和
feature scaling so that the
特征规范化，使得
features, X1 and X2,
特征X1和X2
should have zero mean and
均值为0
should have comparable ranges of values.
数值在可比较的范围之内
I've already done this for this
在这个例子里，我已经这么做了
example, but I'll come
但是
back to this later and talk more
在后面，我将回过来，讨论更多的
about feature scaling and mean normalization in the context of PCA later.
PCA背景下的特征规范化和均值归一化问题
Coming back to this example,
回到这个例子
in contrast to the red
对比
lines that I just drew here's
我刚画好的红线
a different line onto which I could project my data.
这是我对数据进行投影的一条不同的直线
This magenta line.
这条品红色的线
And as you can see, you
如你所见
know, this magenta line is a
你知道，这条品红色直线
much worse direction onto which to project my data, right?
是一个非常糟糕的方向来投影我的数据，对吧？
So if I were to project my
所以，如果我将数据
data onto the magenta
投影到这条品红色的直线上
line, like the other set of points like that.
像我们刚才做的那样
And the projection errors, that
这样，投影误差
is these blue line segments would be huge.
就是这些蓝色的线段，将会很大
So these points have to
所以，这些点将会
move a huge distance in
移动很长一段距离
order to get onto
才能投影到
the, in order to
才能
get projected onto the magenta line.
投影到这条品红色直线上
And so that's why PCA
因此，这就是为什么PCA
principle component analysis would choose
主成分分析方法会选择
something like the red line
红色的这条直线
rather than like the magenta line down here.
而不是品红色的这条直线
Let's write out the PCA problem a little more formally.
我们正式一点地写出PCA问题
The goal of PCA if we
PCA的目标是
want to reduce data from two-
将数据从二维
dimensional to one-dimensional is
降到一维
we're going to try to find
我们将试着寻找
a vector, that is
一个向量
a vector Ui
向量Ui
which is going to be in Rn,
属于Rn空间中的向量
so that would be in R2 in this case,
在这个例子中是R2空间中的
going to find direction onto
寻找一个对数据进行投影的方向
which to project the data so as to minimize the projection error.
使得投影误差能够最小
So in this example I'm
在这个例子里
hoping that PCA will find this
希望PCA寻找到
vector, which I'm going
向量，我将它叫做
to call U1, so that
U1，所以
when I project the data onto
当我把数据投影到
the line that I defined
我定义的这条直线
by extending out this vector,
通过延长这个向量得到的直线
I end up with pretty small
最后我得到非常小的
reconstruction errors and reference
重建误差
data looks like this.
参考数据看上去是这样的
And by the way,
此外
I should mention that whether PCA
我应该指出的是，无论PCA
gives me U1 or negative U1, it doesn't matter.
给出的是这个U1，还是负的U1，都没关系
So if it gives me a positive
如果它给出的是正的向量
vector in this direction that's fine, if it gives me,
在这个方向上，这没问题
sort of the opposite vector facing
如果给出的是相反的向量
in the opposite direction, so that
在相反的方向上
would be -U1, draw that in
也就是-U1，用蓝色来画
blue instead, whether it gives me positive
无论给的是正的
U1 negative U1,
还是负的U1
it doesn't matter, because each of
都没关系，因为
these vectors defines the
每一个方向都定义了
same red line onto which
相同的红色直线
I'm projecting my data. So this
也就是我将投影的方向
is a case of reducing data
这就是将
from 2 dimensional to 1 dimensional.
2维数据降到1维的例子
In the more general case we
更一般的情况是
have N dimensional data and
我们有N维的数据
we want to reduce it K dimensions.
想降到K维
In that case, we want to
在这种情况下
find not just a single vector
我们不仅仅只寻找单个的向量
onto which to project the data
来对数据进行投影
but we want to find K dimensions
我们想寻找K个方向
onto which to project the data.
来对数据进行投影
So as to minimize this projection error.
为了最小化投影误差
So here's an example.
这是一个例子
If I have a 3D point
如果我有3维数据点
cloud like this then maybe
比如说像这样的
what I want to do is find
我想要做的是
vectors, sorry find a pair of vectors,
寻找向量，对不起，是寻找两个向量
and I'm gonna call these vectors
我将这些向量叫做...
lets draw these in red, I'm going
我们用红线画出来
to find a pair of vectors,
我要寻找两个向量
extending for the origin here's
从原点延伸出来
U1, and here's
这是U1
my second vector U2,
这是第二个向量U2
and together these two
这两个向量一起
vectors define a plane,
定义了一个平面
or they define a 2D surface,
或者说，定义了一个2维平面
kind of like this, sort of,
类似于这样的
2D surface, onto which I'm going to project my data.
2维平面，我将把数据投影到上面
For those of you that are
对于你们其中
familiar with linear algebra, for
熟悉线性代数的人来说
those of you that are really experts
对于你们其中真的
in linear algebra, the formal
精通线性代数的人来说，
definition of this is that
对这个正式的定义是
we're going to find a set of
我们将寻找一组向量
vectors, U1 U2 maybe up
U1，U2，也许
to Uk, and what
一直到Uk
we're going to do is project
我们将要做的是
the data onto the linear
将数据投影到
subspace spanned by this set of k vectors.
这k个向量张开的线性子空间上
But if you are not familiar
但是如果你不熟悉
with linear algebra, just think
线性代数，那就想成是
of it as finding k directions
寻找k个方向
instead of just one direction, onto which to project the data.
而不是只寻找一个方向，对数据进行投影
So, finding a k-dimensional surface,
所以，寻找一个k维的平面
really finding a 2D plane
在这里是寻找2维的平面
in this case, shown in this
如图所示
figure, where we can
这里我们用
define the position of the points in the plane using k directions.
k个方向来定义平面中这些点的位置
That's why for PCA, we
这就是为什么，对于PCA
want to find k vectors onto which to project the data.
我们要寻找k个向量来对数据进行投影
And so, more formally, in
因此，更正式一点的说
PCA what we want
在PCA中，我们想做的就是
to do is find this way
寻找到这种方式
to project the data so as
对数据进行投影
to minimize the, sort of,
进而最小化投影距离
projection distance, which is distance between points and projections.
也就是数据点和投影后的点之间的距离
In this so 3D example,
在这个3维的例子里
too, given a point we
给定一个点
would take the point and project
我们想将这个点
it onto this 2D surface.
投影到2维平面上
When you're done with that,
当你完成了那个
and so the projection error would
因此投影误差就是
be, you know, the distance between the
也就是
point and where it gets projected down.
这点与投影到
to my 2D surface,
2维平面之后的点之间的距离
and so what PCA does is it'll
因此PCA做的是
try to find a line or
寻找一条直线
plane or whatever onto which
或者平面，诸如此类等等
to project the data, to try
对数据进行投影
to minimize that squared projection,
来最小化平方投影
that 90 degree, or that orthogonal projection error.
90度的或者正交的投影误差
Finally, one question that I
最后
sometimes get asked is how
一个我有时会被问到的问题是
does PCA relate to
PCA和线性回归有怎么样的关系？
linear regression, because when explaining
因为当我解释PCA的时候
PCA I sometimes end up
我有时候会以
drawing diagrams like these and that looks a little bit like linear regression.
画这样的图表来结束，看上去有点像线性回归
It turns out PCA is not
但是，事实是
linear regression, and despite
PCA不是线性回国
some cosmetic similarity these are actually totally different algorithms.
尽管看上去有一些相似性，但是它们确实是两种不同的算法
If we were doing linear regression
如果我们做线性回国
what we would do would be, on
我们 做的是
the left we would be trying
看左边，我们想要
to predict the value of some
在给定某个输入特征x的情况下
variable y given some input
预测某个变量y的数值
features x. And so linear
因此，对于线性回归
regression, what we're doing
我们想做的是
is we're fitting a straight line
拟合一条直线
so as to minimize the squared
来最小化
error between a point and the straight line.
点和直线之间的平方误差
And so what we'd be minimizing
所以我们要最小化的是
would be the squared magnitude of these blue lines.
这些蓝线幅值的平方
And notice I'm drawing these
注意我画的这些
blue lines vertically, that they
蓝色的垂直线
are the vertical distance between
这是垂直距离
a point and the value
它是某个点
predicted by the hypothesis, whereas in
与通过假设的得到的其预测值之间的距离
contrast, in PCA, what it
与此想反
does is it tries to
PCA要做的是
minimize the magnitude of these blue lines,
最小化这些蓝色直线的幅值
which are drawn at an angle,
倾斜地画出来的
these are really the shortest orthogonal
这实际上是最短的
distances, the shortest distance between
直角距离
the point X and this
点X
red line, and this
跟红色直线之间的最短距离
gives very different effects, depending
这是一种非常不同的效果
on the data set.
取决于数据集
And more generally generally and
更更更一般的是
more generally when you're doing
当你做
linear regression there is this
线性回归的时候，有一个
distinguished variable y that
特别的变量y
we're trying to predict, all that
是我们将要预测的
linear regression is about is taking all the values
线性回归所要做的就是
of X and try to use
用X的所有的值来
that to predict Y. Whereas
预测y
in PCA, there is no
然而在PCA中
distinguished or there is
没有这么一个特别的或者
no special variable Y that
特殊的变量y
we're trying to predict, and instead
是我们要预测的
we have a list of features
我们所拥有的是
x1, x2, and so on
特征x1，x2，等
up to xN, and all of
一直到xN
these features are treated equally.
所有的这些特征都是被同样地对待
So, no one of them is special.
因此，它们中没有一个是特殊的
As one last example, if I
最后一个例子中
have three-dimensional data, and
如果我有3维数据
I want to reduce data from
我要将这些数据
3D to 2D, so maybe
从3维降到2维
I want to find two directions,
我就要找到2个方向
you know, u1, and u2,
也就是u1和u2
onto which to project my data,
将数据投影到它们上面
then what I have is I
然后我得到的是
have three features, x1, x2,
我有3个特征，x1，x2
x3, and all of these are treated alike.
x3，所有的这些都是被同样地对待
All of these are treated symmetrically
这些都是被均等地对待
and there is no special variable
没有特殊的变量
y that I'm trying to predict.
y，需要被预测
And so PCA is not
因此，PCA
linear regression, and even
不是线性回归
though at some cosmetic level they
尽管一定程度的相似性
might look related, these are
使得它们看上去是有关联的
actually very different algorithms. So,
但它们实际上非常不同的算法
hopefully you now understand what
因此，希望你们能理解
PCA is doing: it's trying
PCA是做什么的
to find a lower dimensional
它是寻找到一个低维的平面
surface onto which to project
对数据进行投影
the data so as to
以便
minimize this squared projection error,
最小化投影误差的平方
to minimize the squared distance between
最小化每个点
each point and the location of where it gets projected.
与投影后的对应点之间的距离的平方值
In the next video we'll start
在下一段视频中
to talk about how to actually
我们将开始讨论
find this lower dimensional surface
如果真正地找到这个低维平面
onto which to project the data.
来对数据进行投影